Lucas J. Sterzinger

Curriculum Vitae

Address removed for Public CV https://github.com/lsterzinger

INTEREST STATEMENT

I am an Atmospheric Science PhD candidate at UC Davis, graduating 12/2022. My research focuses on numerical modelling of clouds and precipitation processes. I am passionate about open source and open science. I am involved in the Kerchunk Python library, which makes existing cloud-hosted datasets more accessible. I want to work and do research at the intersection of geoscience, data science, and software development.

EDUCATION

PhD, Atmospheric Science University of California, Davis, Davis, CA Anticipated Graduation: Fall 2022

2017 - Present

Bachelor of Science, Atmospheric Sciences University of North Dakota, Grand Forks, ND

Minor: Mathematics

Bachelor of Science, Aeronautics

2012 - 2017

2012 - 2017

University of North Dakota, Grand Forks, ND

TECHNICAL

Languages & Software: Python, Julia, Fortran Operating Systems: Unix/Linux, MacOS, Windows Software Packages:

- PyRAMS (maintainer) Package for working with RAMS model data
- Kerchunk (contributor) Cloud performant access to NetCDF4 data

PUBLICATIONS

Do arctic mixed-phase clouds sometimes dissipate due to insufficient aerosol? Evidence from comparisons between observations and idealized simulations Sterzinger, L. J., Sedlar, J., Guy, H., Neely III, R., & Igel, A. L.

2022

Atmospheric Chemistry and Physics

https://doi.org/10.5194/acp-2022-36

The Effects of Ice Habit on Simulated Orographic Snowfall The Effects of Ice Habit on Simulated Orographic Snowfall The Effects of Ice Habit on Simulated Orographic Snowfall 2021

Models in the Cloud: A Cost Exploration of Cloud Computing for the Atmospheric Sciences

2017

News@Unidata Blog

https://www.unidata.ucar.edu/blogs/news/entry/models-in-the-cloud-a

WORK EXPERIENCE

Graduate Student Researcher

Atmospheric Science Graduate Group, UC Davis

Dr. Adele Igel, Faculty Advisor

- Works on various research related to cloud and precipitation physics. Projects include:
 - Effect of ice crystal habit (shape) on orographic snowfall in the Sierra Nevada Mountains.
 (Funding: Internal)
 - Examining the relationship between mixed-phase Arctic cloud dissipation and aerosol properties. (Funding: DOE ASR; A. Igel, PI)
 - Assessing relative impacts on aerosol contained within the boundary layer and free troposphere
 on the microphysics and other properties of Arctic mixed-phase clouds. (Funding: DOE ASR;
 A. Igel, PI)

Intern Summer 2021

Summer Internship in Parallel Computational Science (SIParCS) National Center for Atmospheric Research (NCAR), Boulder, CO

- Worked with Chelle Gentemann (Farallon Inst./NASA TOPS), Kevin Paul (NCAR), Julia Kent (NCAR), Rich Signell (USGS) and Martin Durant (Anaconda Inc.) on the development of the Kerchunk software library and its applicability and performance accessing cloud-hosted NOAA/NASA satellite data.
- Wrote documentation, blog posts, and example code on how to get started using Kerchunk published open-source on GitHub.

Undergraduate Research Assistant

2016 - 2017

2017 - Present

Dept. of Atmospheric Sciences, University of N. Dakota

Dr. Gretchen Mullendore, Faculty Advisor

• Worked on the "Big Weather Web" project examining potential uses for cloud computing infrastructure for numerical weather prediction.

Undergraduate Teaching Assistant

2015 - 2017

Dept. of Atmospheric Sciences, University of N. Dakota

• Independently taught Introduction to Meteorology lab, complete with weekly lectures and laboratory experiments.

Technical Support Specialist

2012 - 2017

Univ. of N. Dakota School of Medicine and Health Sciences

• Responsible for direct technology support to faculty, staff, and students. Also worked on managing video conference sytems, networks, and servers.

SERVICE

UC Davis Graduate Student Association

• General Assembly Representative

2019-2022

• Elections Committee

2019-2020

UC Davis Academic Senate Committee on Information Technology	
Graduate Student Representative	2020-2021
SELECTED CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS	
Open Science Success Stories	Dec. 2022
Session Co-Convener American Geophysics Union Fall Meeting 2022 - Chicago, IL	
Arctic Mixed-Phase Clouds Sometimes Dissipate Due to Insufficient Aerosol - Evidence from Idealized Large Eddy Simulations Oral Presentation European Geosciences Union General Assembly 2022 - Vienna, Austria	May 2022
Arctic Mixed-Phase Clouds Sometimes Dissipate due to Insufficient Aerosol: Evidence from Idealized Large Eddy Simulations Oral Presentation 2nd QuIESCENT Workshop - Tromsø, Norway	Apr. 2022
Fake it until you make it — Reading GOES NetCDF4 data on AWS S3 as Zarr for rapid data access Oral Presentation and Interactive Workshop 2021 ESIP January Meeting	Jan. 2022
Cloud-performant reading of NetCDF4/HDF5/Grib2 using the Zarr library Oral Presentation American Geophysics Union Fall Meeting 2021 - Online	Dec. 2021
Effects of Aerosol Concentration on the Dissipation of Arctic Mixed-Phase Clouds eLightning American Geophysics Union Fall Meeting 2020 - Online	Dec. 2020

MEMBERSHIPS

American Meteorological Society American Geophysics Union European Geosciences Union

LANGUAGES

English

French (Bilingual Fluency)